<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
<book code="JON" style="id">E2T (Easy to Translate Bible)</book>
<para style="mt1">This book is the account about Jonah, when he disobeyed God, was three days in a big fish\'s belly, and finally went to warn the wicked people in Nineveh city that God was going to destroy them. We call this book JONAH.</para>
<chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JON 1" />
<para style="s1">Jonah refuses to obey Yahweh</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="1" style="v" sid="JON 1:1" />
<char style="add"> One day</char> Yahweh said to the <char style="add">prophet</char> Jonah, Amittai's son, 
<verse eid="JON 1:1" />
<verse number="2" style="v" sid="JON 1:2" />
 "I have seen how wicked are <char style="add">the people who live in</char> the great city called Nineveh. Therefore, go there and warn the people that I am planning to destroy their city because they d sinned."
<note caller="*One day* Yahweh said to the *prophet *Jonah, Amittai’s son
" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR *There was a prophet in Israel named* Jonah who was Amittai's son. *One day* Yahweh said to him: </char></note>
<note caller="*One day* Yahweh said to the *prophet *Jonah, Amittai’s son
" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">Use words that will indicate that this is a real, historical story. Do not use words that might communicate that this is a folk tale, a fake story or a myth. </char></note>
<note caller="the great city called Nineveh" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR the large/important city called Nineveh* in the Assyria kingdom* </char></note>
<note caller="the great city called Nineveh" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Jonah 3:1 </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:2" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="3" style="v" sid="JON 1:3" />
 But <char style="add">Jonah</char> did not go <char style="add">to Nineveh</char>. <char style="add">Instead, he</char> went in the direction opposite to where Yahweh told him to go. He went (down) to Joppa <char style="add">city</char>. There he paid the fare to travel on a ship that was going to Tarshish <char style="add">city</char>. Jonah wanted to escape from Yahweh and avoid doing what Yahweh had told him to do. He got on the ship, <char style="add">and then he went down to a lower deck inside the ship. He lay down, and went to sleep.</char>
<note caller="went (down)
" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR went  
OR traveled
 </char></note>
<note caller="went (down)
" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">Jonah had to travel from a high elevation (Jerusalem city) down to Joppa city which was a low elevation. Joppa was at sea level where a ship could be docked.The repeated “down” communicates that Jonah is going down from Yahweh’s exalted/”up” position. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:3" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="4" style="v" sid="JON 1:4" />
 Then Yahweh caused a very strong wind to blow. There was such a violent storm that <char style="add">the sailors thought</char> the ship would break apart. 
<verse eid="JON 1:4" />
<verse number="5" style="v" sid="JON 1:5" />
 The sailors were very frightened. So, they each started to pray to their own gods <char style="add">to save them</char>. Then they threw the cargo into the sea to make the ship lighter <char style="add">in order that it would not sink easily</char>.
<note caller="they each started to pray to their own gods" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR each one started to pray to his own god </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:5" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="6" style="v" sid="JON 1:6" />
 Then the captain went <char style="add">down</char> to where Jonah was sleeping deeply. He <char style="add">awoke him and</char> said to him. "You should not be sleeping <char style="add">during a storm like this one!</char> Get up and pray to your god! Perhaps he will pity us and save us, so that we will not drown!" 
<verse eid="JON 1:6" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="7" style="v" sid="JON 1:7" />
 Then the sailors said to each other, "We must cast lots to determine who has caused all this trouble!" So they did that, and the lots showed that Jonah had caused the storm. 
<verse eid="JON 1:7" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="8" style="v" sid="JON 1:8" />
 So <char style="add">various ones among</char> them asked Jonah, "Are you the one who has caused all this trouble for us?" "What work do you do?" "Where are you coming from?" "What country and what people-group do you belong to?"
<note caller="cast lots" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR throw objects/lots/dice
OR shake in a container small objects that we have all marked and then let one fall out </char></note>
<note caller="cast lots" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Proverbs 16.33; Acts 1:26 </char></note>
<note caller="caused all this trouble" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR offended the god that caused the storm </char></note>
<note caller="the lots showed that Jonah had caused the storm" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR the dice identified Jonah
OR  the *object *with Jonah’s mark *fell out from the bag/container* </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:8" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="9" style="v" sid="JON 1:9" />
 Jonah replied, "I am a Hebrew. I worship Yahweh, who lives in heaven. He is the God who made the sea and the land. I am trying to escape from <char style="add">doing what</char> Yahweh <char style="add">told me to do</char>."
<note caller="I am a Hebrew" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR I am from the Hebrew people-group. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:9" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="10" style="v" sid="JON 1:10" />
 After/When the sailors heard that, they were <char style="add">more</char> terrified. So, they asked him, "Do you realize what trouble you have caused?"
<verse eid="JON 1:10" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="11" style="v" sid="JON 1:11" />
 The storm kept getting worse, and the waves kept getting bigger. So, one sailor among them asked Jonah, "What must we do <char style="add">to you, so that your god</char> will make the sea become calm?"
<verse eid="JON 1:11" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="12" style="v" sid="JON 1:12" />
 Jonah replied to them, "Pick me up and throw me into the sea. <char style="add">If you do that,</char> then the sea will become calm. I know that this terrible storm is caused by my <char style="add">not doing what Yahweh told me to do</char>."
<verse eid="JON 1:12" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="13" style="v" sid="JON 1:13" />
 But the sailors <char style="add">did not want to do that. Instead,</char> they tried hard to row the ship back to land. But <char style="add">they could not do so, because</char> the storm continued to get worse.
<note caller="*did not want to do that*" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR did not want to throw Jonah into the sea </char></note>
<note caller="row the ship" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR pull the ship
OR paddle the ship
OR get the ship </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:13" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="14" style="v" sid="JON 1:14" />
 Therefore, the sailors prayed to Yahweh, "O Yahweh, please do not cause us to drown after we cause this man to die. O Yahweh, we beg you, do not consider us to be guilty when we cause this man to die. We know that you have sent this storm for your own good reasons."
<note caller="you have sent this storm for your own good reasons" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR you have done what you wanted to do </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:14" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="15" style="v" sid="JON 1:15" />
 Then they picked Jonah up and threw him into the sea. Then the sea became calm. 
<verse eid="JON 1:15" />
<verse number="16" style="v" sid="JON 1:16" />
 When that happened, the sailors became greatly awed at/respected Yahweh's power. So, they offered a sacrifice to Yahweh. They also vowed to him that they would do things that would please him.
<note caller="became greatly awed at Yahweh’s power" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR greatly respected Yahweh’s power </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:16" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="17" style="v" sid="JON 1:17" />
<char style="add"> While they were doing that,</char> Yahweh sent a huge fish that swallowed Jonah. Then Jonah was inside the fish's belly for three days and three nights.
<note caller="that swallowed Jonah" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">*OR that swallowed Jonah alive
OR who put Jonah in his mouth and downed him* </char></note>
<note caller="that swallowed Jonah" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">The fish swallowed Jonah without chewing or biting him. The fish did not eat Jonah. </char></note>
<note caller="for three days and three nights" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR three days </char></note>
<note caller="for three days and three nights" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Matthew 12:40 </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 1:17" />
</para>
<chapter eid="JON 1" />
<chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JON 2" />
<para style="s2">Jonah thanks Yahweh for rescuing him</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="1" style="v" sid="JON 2:1" />
 While Jonah was inside the huge fish, he prayed to Yahweh God, <char style="add">whom he worshiped</char>. <char style="add">This is what Jonah reported later:</char>
<note caller="*This is what Jonah reported later:   *" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR (omit) </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:1" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="2" style="v" sid="JON 2:2" />
 Jonah said, "Yahweh, when I was greatly distressed there <char style="add">in the fish belly</char>, I prayed to you, and you heard what I prayed. When I was about to descend way down into the place where dead people go, you heard me when I called out for you to help/save me. 
<note caller="Jonah said" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR  Jonah prayed </char></note>
<note caller="Jonah said" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">Jonah’s prayer is a Hebrew poem or song.  If you want to  create a poem in your language from the content of Jonah’s prayer, or sing Jonah’s song in your language, that would be very appropriate </char></note>
<note caller="about to descend way down into the place where dead people go" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR when I almost died 
OR when I was as good as dead </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:2" />
<verse number="3" style="v" sid="JON 2:3" />
 You threw me down into the deep water, down to the sea's bottom. The sea currents swirled around me, and the huge waves crashed above me. 
<note caller="You threw me" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR You caused men to throw me </char></note>
<note caller="the huge waves crashed above me" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR You buried me under crashing waves </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:3" />
<verse number="4" style="v" sid="JON 2:4" />
 Then I thought/said, 'Although You have banished me, Yet I will go to see your holy temple again!'
<note caller="Then I thought/said, ‘Although You" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR Then I thought that although You
 </char></note>
<note caller="Then I thought/said, ‘Although You" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Jonah 2:7 </char></note>
<note caller="Then I thought/said, ‘Although You" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">Since Jonah is thinking and not speaking out loud, in your translation, you might want to use an indirect quote rather than a direct speech quote. </char></note>
<note caller="You have banished me" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR You have expelled/cast me away from your presence/sight </char></note>
<note caller="Yet I will" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR But surely I will  </char></note>
<note caller="Yet I will" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">There is a text translation issue with this part of verse 4.  The Hebrew text introduces Jonah’s second thought with a word meaning ‘yet’ or ‘surely’, expressing hope. But there is one alternate Greek translation from the Hebrew that uses a word meaning ‘how’, expressing a sense of hopelessness, that Jonah might never again see the Lord.  English versions are divided in how they render this meaning.  Many follow the second alternative, even though it has little textual support.  So, it is recommended that you follow the Hebrew text and the options given here.  (TN Jonah) </char></note>
<note caller="to see your holy temple again" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR to see the holy place where you/Yahweh live </char></note>
<note caller="to see your holy temple again" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">There is disagreement among scholars concerning whether the temple mentioned in chapter 2, verses 4 and 7, refers to the earthly temple in Jerusalem, or to Yahweh’s eternal dwelling place in heaven. So, if possible, avoid referring to the location of the temple in these verses. In both verses, the sense seems to be “the holy place where you (the Lord) live.” (TN Jonah, Hohulin, 2000)Both the Jerusalem temple and the temple in heaven were true dwelling places for Yahweh. The Glory of Yahweh Himself used to dwell in the tabernacle and later in the temple. Jonah had “come down” from Jerusalem to Joppa, and contemplated returning to Jerusalem. In the context of Jewish “cosmic geography,” Judah was Yahweh’s land, and Nineveh was a dwelling place for demons.  GC </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:4" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="5" style="v" sid="JON 2:5" />
 "The water surrounded me, and threatened to drown me. Seaweed was wrapped around my head. 
<note caller="seaweed" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR sea plants </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:5" />
<verse number="6" style="v" sid="JON 2:6" />
 I sank down to where the mountains start rising from the sea bottom. I thought that it would be as though my body would forever be in a prison inside the earth below me. But you, Yahweh God, whom I worship, you rescued me from going down to the place where the dead go. 
<note caller="rescued me from going down to the place where the dead go" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR rescued me from death  
OR rescued me back from dying </char></note>
<note caller="rescued me from going down to the place where the dead go" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">We do not know if Jonah died physically or only metaphorically (figuratively speaking). </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:6" />
<verse number="7" style="v" sid="JON 2:7" />
 When I was almost dead, Yahweh, I thought about you. You heard my prayer <char style="add">to you</char>, up there where you are, in your holy temple. 
<note caller="When I was almost dead" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR As I was dying </char></note>
<note caller="When I was almost dead" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Jonah 2:4 </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:7" />
<verse number="8" style="v" sid="JON 2:8" />
 All those who worship worthless idols are rejecting you, the one who could act kindly toward them. 
<note caller="who could act kindly" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">*OR who is faithful to keep his promises
* </char></note>
<note caller="who could act kindly" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">*The Hebrew word here is khesed*. (Here rendered kindly) The common meaning of the Hebrew term *khesed *seems to include loyalty or reliability, faithfulness and kindness or steady compassion. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:8" />
<verse number="9" style="v" sid="JON 2:9" />
 But I will sing to thank you, and I will offer a sacrifice to thank you, Yahweh. I will surely do what I have solemnly promised to do. Yahweh, you are the only one who is able to save us."
<note caller="But I" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR But, as for me, I </char></note>
<note caller="offer a sacrifice to thank you" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR offer to sacrifice animals to thank you </char></note>
<note caller="offer a sacrifice to thank you" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">In ancient times, pagans commonly offered sacrifices to bribe their gods or to placate them. In Israel, however, sacrifices were for purifying dirty/polluted things, worshiping and honoring Yahweh, and expressing thanks to Yahweh.  </char></note>
<note caller="Yahweh, you are the only one who is able to save us" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR Because it is Yahweh alone who saves anyone.      </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 2:9" />
</para>
<chapter eid="JON 2" />
<chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JON 3" />
<para style="s3">The people in Nineveh repented after Jonah warned them</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="1" style="v" sid="JON 3:1" />
 Then Yahweh said to Jonah a second time, saying, 
<verse eid="JON 3:1" />
<verse number="2" style="v" sid="JON 3:2" />
 "Go immediately to that great city called Nineveh, and tell the people who live there the message that I gave you <char style="add">previously</char>."
<note caller="that great city" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR   that large/important city </char></note>
<note caller="that great city" style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Jonah 1:2 </char></note>
<note caller="that great city" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">How you described the city in Jonah 1:2, be consistent to describe it the same way here.   </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 3:2" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="3" style="v" sid="JON 3:3" />
 So, <char style="add">this time</char> Jonah obeyed Yahweh, and he went to Nineveh. That city was so big that <char style="add">a person</char> <char style="add">had to walk</char> for three days to <char style="add">go</char> <char style="add">everywhere in</char> it.
<note caller="a person had to walk for three days to go everywhere in it" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR  it took three days to walk through it
OR it took three days for a person to visit/see it all </char></note>
<note caller="a person had to walk for three days to go everywhere in it" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">The walls surrounding Nineveh extended five kilometers around, so a person could walk around the city in a few hours. Jonah’s three-day walk likely refers to walking about inside the city. The number three is important to retain in this story. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 3:3" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="4" style="v" sid="JON 3:4" />
 On the first day <char style="add">after</char> Jonah <char style="add">arrived</char>, he <char style="add">began walking</char> through the city. He started proclaiming to the people, "Forty days from now, <char style="add">God</char> will destroy Nineveh!" 
<verse eid="JON 3:4" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="5" style="v" sid="JON 3:5" />
 The people in Nineveh believed God's <char style="add">message</char>. They <char style="add">all</char> decided that everyone should stop eating food, and they must dress themselves with old/rough clothes, <char style="add">to show that they were sorry for having sinned</char>.  So, <char style="add">everyone</char>, including important people and unimportant people, <char style="add">did so</char>.
<note caller="stop eating food" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR fast 
OR abstain from food </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 3:5" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="6" style="v" sid="JON 3:6" />
 Nineveh's king heard the news about Jonah and <char style="add">what the people were doing</char>. <char style="add">So,</char> he took off his royal robes, and <char style="add">he also</char> put on old/rough clothes. He left his palace, and sat down on <char style="add">cold</char> ashes, <char style="add">to humble himself and show that he also was sorry for having sinned</char>. 
<verse eid="JON 3:6" />
<verse number="7" style="v" sid="JON 3:7" />
 Then he sent messengers to proclaim to <char style="add">everyone in</char> Nineveh:
<verse eid="JON 3:7" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="7" style="v" sid="JON 3:7" />
 "My advisors and I have decreed that no one may eat or drink anything. Do not even allow your animals to eat or drink. 
<verse eid="JON 3:7" />
<verse number="8" style="v" sid="JON 3:8" />
 Instead, every person must put on old/rough cloth. <char style="add">Put old/rough cloth on</char> your animals, <char style="add">too</char>. Then everyone must pray fervently to God. And everyone must stop doing evil actions/things, and stop acting violently <char style="add">toward others</char>. 
<verse eid="JON 3:8" />
<verse number="9" style="v" sid="JON 3:9" />
 Perhaps, <char style="add">if everyone does so</char>, then God may change his mind and be merciful <char style="add">to</char> us.  Maybe God will stop being very angry with us, with the result that we will not die."
<verse eid="JON 3:9" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="10" style="v" sid="JON 3:10" />
 When they <char style="add">all did that</char>, God saw what they were doing, and he saw that they had stopped doing evil things. So, <char style="add">he pitied them, and</char> he did not destroy them as he had threatened to do. 
<verse eid="JON 3:10" />
</para>
<chapter eid="JON 3" />
<chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JON 4" />
<para style="s4">Yahweh teaches Jonah that he has/shows mercy and compassion</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="1" style="v" sid="JON 4:1" />
 But when Yahweh did not punish Nineveh, this distressed/displeased Jonah very much! And he became very angry. <char style="add">(The people in Nineveh were not Jews, and Jonah did not think that God should act mercifully toward people who were enemies to the Jews.)</char>
<verse eid="JON 4:1" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="2" style="v" sid="JON 4:2" />
 So, Jonah complained to Yahweh, saying: "O Yahweh, what you have done is what I thought that you would do, before I left home. That is why I <char style="add">decided</char> immediately to run away, and go to Tarshish <char style="add">city</char>. I did so because I knew that you, O God, act very kindly and compassionate <char style="add">toward all people</char>. You do not quickly become angry with people who do evil things. You love people very much, and you change your mind about punishing <char style="add">sinful</char> <char style="add">people</char> <char style="add">when they repent</char>. 
<note caller="complained" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR prayed [with bitterness] </char></note>
<note caller="You love people very much" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR You keep your promises to people </char></note>
<note caller="You love people very much" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">The Hebrew word *khesed *remains the foremost characteristic for God, meaning covenant loyalty. The Greek equivalent is “faithful(ness)”. </char></note>
<note caller="you, O God, act very kindly and compassionate *toward all people*. You do not quickly become angry with people who do evil things. You love people very much, and you change your mind about punishing *sinful people when they repent*." style="f" category="parrallelRef"><char style="ft">Exodus 34:6; Jeremiah 18:1-11 </char></note>
<note caller="you, O God, act very kindly and compassionate *toward all people*. You do not quickly become angry with people who do evil things. You love people very much, and you change your mind about punishing *sinful people when they repent*." style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">Jonah is summarizing a passage about Yahweh that is repeated very often throughout Scripture. </char></note>
<note caller="allow me to die" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR kill me now </char></note>
<note caller="It is not right/good for you to be angry about my not destroying the city" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR Is it right for you to be angry about my not destroying the city?   </char></note>
<note caller="It is not right/good for you to be angry about my not destroying the city" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">In Hebrew, this is a rhetorical question, not a real question. You may translate it either as a strong statement, or as a rhetorical question that is designed to make the listener/reader think. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:2" />
<verse number="3" style="v" sid="JON 4:3" />
 So, now, O Yahweh, <char style="add">because you will not destroy Nineveh city as you said you would,</char> allow me to die. It is better for me to die than to <char style="add">continue to</char> live."
<verse eid="JON 4:3" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="4" style="v" sid="JON 4:4" />
 Yahweh replied, "Why are you angry <char style="add">that I have not destroyed the city</char>?"
<note caller="It is better for me to die than to *continue to* live" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR I do not want to live. I want to die. </char></note>
<note caller="Why are you angry " style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR Is it right for you to be angry
OR There is no good reason for  you to be angry
OR It is not right/good for you to be angry </char></note>
<note caller="Why are you angry " style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">This is a rhetorical question which Yahweh is “asking” Jonah in order to rebuke him and make him change his bad attitude.  You may translate it as a statement if that is a more meaningful way for your language. </char></note>
<note caller="*not destroyed*" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">*OR spared
OR saved* </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:4" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="5" style="v" sid="JON 4:5" />
 Jonah <char style="add">did not reply</char>. He went out from the city to its east <char style="add">side</char>. He made a small shelter so that he could sit under it and be protected from the sun. He sat under the shelter and waited to see what would happen to the city.
<verse eid="JON 4:5" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="6" style="v" sid="JON 4:6" />
 Then Yahweh God caused a vine to grow up <char style="add">immediately</char> to shade Jonah's head from the sun and make him <char style="add">feel</char> more comfortable. Jonah was very happy about <char style="add">having</char> the vine <char style="add">over his head</char>. 
<note caller="He went out from the city to its east *side*" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR He went out through the main gate and sat down near the city (*where he could overlook the city) *    </char></note>
<note caller="He went out from the city to its east *side*" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">The Hebrew word *qedem* may mean ‘front’ or ‘east’. (NET2 note)There is a theme in Scripture, that when people go “east”, this indicates that they are going into exile or separating themselves from Yahweh. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:6" />
<verse number="7" style="v" sid="JON 4:7" />
 But before dawn the next day, God sent a worm that chewed the vine, with the result that the vine withered. 
<verse eid="JON 4:7" />
<verse number="8" style="v" sid="JON 4:8" />
 Then, when the sun rose <char style="add">high in the sky</char>, God sent a very hot wind from the east. The sun shone very strongly on Jonah's head, with the result that he felt faint. He wanted to die, and he said, "It would be better for me to die than to <char style="add">continue to</char> live!"
<note caller="a worm" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR an insect 
OR a bug </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:8" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="9" style="v" sid="JON 4:9" />
 But God asked Jonah, "Is it right/good for you to be angry <char style="add">because the vine died</char>?"
<note caller="Is it right for you to be angry because the plant died?" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR You have no right to be angry just because this plant died/withered 
OR You should not be angry that the plant withered! </char></note>
<note caller="Is it right for you to be angry because the plant died?" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">This may be a rhetorical question, not a real question. </char></note>
<note caller="Yes, it is right!  Now I am very angry and I want to die!" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR I am right to be angry so much that I wish I were dead. </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:9" />
</para>
<para style="p">
<verse number="10" style="v" sid="JON 4:10" />
 But Yahweh said <char style="add">to him</char>, "You feel sorry about my <char style="add">causing</char> that vine <char style="add">to wither</char>, even though you did not make it grow and you did not care for it. It just grew up during one night, and it completely withered during the next night. 
<verse eid="JON 4:10" />
<verse number="11" style="v" sid="JON 4:11" />
 But there are more than 120,000 people in Nineveh who do not know right from wrong <char style="add">(and they are more valuable than that vine)</char>. There are also many animals/livestock/cows <char style="add">in Nineveh</char>. So, it is right for me to show compassion to the people who live in that huge city <char style="add">and not want to destroy them!</char>"
<note caller="who do not know right from wrong" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR who do not know that they are living not knowing about My laws/ways
OR who do not know the difference between their right hand and their left hand </char></note>
<note caller="who do not know right from wrong" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">The Hebrew here says literally, “people who do not know the difference between their right and left hands”. Some scholars think this is referring to children. That is possible, but this is probably an idiom meaning that the people, no matter their age, have no discernment, no education, or no knowledge about God’s teaching on what is true and what is not true. Translate it so that it communicates a clear meaning.  </char></note>
<note caller="there are also many animals/livestock/cows" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR there are also many herds/cattle (*and none among these have done anything to displease me.*)  </char></note>
<note caller=" it is right for me" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR Is it not right/good for me
OR Therefore I should </char></note>
<note caller=" it is right for me" style="f" category="extra"><char style="ft">This may be a rhetorical question or a real question that Yahweh asks Jonah, so that Jonah will reconsider and repent of his bad attitude. (God is making a strong distinction between Jonah's attitude and his behavior.) But we do not hear Jonah’s response. The book intentionally ends with this question or statement, so that people hearing this book will think about it for themselves. </char></note>
<note caller="show compassion to" style="f" category="content"><char style="ft">OR feel sorry for </char></note>
<verse eid="JON 4:11" />
</para>
<chapter eid="JON 4" />
<note caller="+" style="f" category="overview"><char style="ft">Passage Overview:
Once again, Yahweh commands his prophet Jonah to go to Israel’s enemies In Nineveh city. He was supposed to preach to them to repent so that God  would not destroy them. 
This time, Jonah obeys the Lord, but he is not happy when the Ninevites repent and Yahweh does not destroy them. Jonah is angry that the city is saved, so Yahweh sends a hot wind, a leafy vine and a
worm to try and reason with Jonah about his bad attitude and lack of compassion for people. 
Background Info:
Historical context:
Prominent Themes: </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="background_info"><char style="ft">● The pagan kingdom of Assyria, of which Nineveh was the capitol, was an enemy nation to Israel. Assyria raided and abused other nations. Nineveh was directly north of Israel, accessible by land travel.  </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="historical_context"><char style="ft">● (2Kings 14:25) Jonah, a Jewish prophet of Yahweh, was alive during the reign of Jeroboam II, king of Israel, about 700 years before Jesus' birth.
● Sometime after Jonah's story, about 615 B.C., the prophet Nahum prophesied the downfall of Assyria and Nineveh (Nahum 1-3).. 
● In 612 B.C. God destroyed Nineveh for their wicked ways. (Their repentance did not last long.) </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="prominent_themes:"><char style="ft">● God wants people in all nations to repent and so to be saved.
● God is compassionate and patient. 
● Psalm 135:6 shows God’s sovereign power by using/commanding, for his purposes, big and small creatures, plants and human devices for discerning (i.e., casting lots), the sea and wind, wicked people, to teach people about himself.
● Jeremiah 18:7-10 shows how God can and does change his mind (repent) about doing what he said he would do depending on people’s actions, responses and prayers.  </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="overview"><char style="ft">Passage Overview:
Yahweh commands his prophet Jonah to go to Israel’s enemies In Nineveh city. He was supposed to preach to them to repent so that God  would not destroy them. 
Jonah refuses Yahweh’s command and tries to run away, going in the opposite direction. 
Yahweh sends storms, people and animals to redirect Jonah, causing him to repent and obey. 
Background Info:
Historical context:
Prominent Themes: </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="background_info"><char style="ft">● Jonah was thrown into the ocean and a large fish swallowed him alive. Now he prays to Yahweh from inside the fish. </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="historical_context"><char style="ft">● Jonah is inside a large fish for 3 days and 3 nights praying/repenting, and then Yahweh causes him to be “raised/resurrected” back to life which will be a signal for Messiah </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="prominent_themes:"><char style="ft">● God is compassionate and patient. 
● God spoke through Jonah's words, and he also used Jonah's life as a prophetic message to signal the identity of the promised Messiah (Matt. 12:40). </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="overview"><char style="ft">Passage Overview:
Yahweh commands his prophet Jonah to go to Israel’s enemies In Nineveh city. He was supposed to preach to them to repent so that God  would not destroy them. 
Jonah refuses Yahweh’s command and tries to run away, going in the opposite direction. 
Yahweh sends storms, people and animals to redirect Jonah, causing him to repent and obey. 
Background Info:
Historical context:
Prominent Themes: </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="background_info"><char style="ft">● The pagan kingdom of Assyria, for which Nineveh was the capitol, was an enemy nation to Israel. Assyria raided and abused other nations. Nineveh was directly north of Israel, accessible by land travel. 
● Tarshish was far to the west of Israel, accessible only by boat travel, across the Mediterranean Sea. </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="historical_context"><char style="ft">● (2Kings 14:25) Jonah, a Jewish prophet of Yahweh, was alive during the reign of Jeroboam II, king of Israel, about 700 years before Jesus' birth.
● Sometime after Jonah's story, about 615 B.C., the prophet Nahum prophesied the downfall of Assyria and Nineveh (Nahum 1-3).. 
● In 612 B.C. God destroyed Nineveh for their wicked ways. (Their repentance did not last long.) </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="prominent_themes:"><char style="ft">● down versus up; the chaotic sea versus the “safe” dry land
● God wants people in all nations to repent and so to be saved.
● God is compassionate and patient. 
● God spoke through Jonah's words, and he also used Jonah's life as a prophetic message to signal the identity of the promised Messiah (Matt. 12:40).
● Psalm 135:6 shows God’s sovereign power by using/commanding, for his purposes, big and small creatures, plants and human devices for discerning (i.e., casting lots), the sea and wind, wicked people, to teach people about himself.
● Jeremiah 18:7-10 shows how God can and does change his mind (repent) about doing what he said he would do depending on people’s actions, responses and prayers.  </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="overview"><char style="ft">Passage Overview:
Once again, Yahweh commands his prophet Jonah to go to Israel’s enemies In Nineveh city. He was supposed to preach to them to repent so that God  would not destroy them. 
This time, Jonah obeys the Lord, but he is not happy when the Ninevites repent and Yahweh does not destroy them. Jonah is angry that the city is saved, so Yahweh sends a hot wind, a leafy vine and a
worm to try and reason with Jonah about his bad attitude and lack of compassion for people. 
Background Info:
Historical context:
Prominent Themes: </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="background_info"><char style="ft">● The pagan kingdom of Assyria, of which Nineveh was the capitol, was an enemy nation to Israel. Assyria raided and abused other nations. Nineveh was directly north of Israel, accessible by land travel.  </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="historical_context"><char style="ft">● Sometime after Jonah's story, about 615 B.C., the prophet Nahum prophesied the downfall of Assyria and Nineveh (Nahum 1-3).. 
● In 612 B.C. God destroyed Nineveh for their wicked ways. (Their repentance did not last long.) </char></note>
<note caller="+" style="f" category="prominent_themes:"><char style="ft">● God wants people in all nations to repent and so to be saved.
● God is compassionate and patient. 
● Psalm 135:6 shows God’s sovereign power by using/commanding, for his purposes, big and small creatures, plants and human devices for discerning (i.e., casting lots), the sea and wind, wicked people, to teach people about himself.
● As in Jonah, Jeremiah 18:7-10 shows how God can and does change his mind (repent) about doing what he said he would do depending on people’s actions, responses and prayers.  </char></note>

</usx>